so we said that the SMT processor is not
that much more expensive than a single
threaded processor that has the same
issue it and everything let's see what
the hardware changes for SMT look like
so that we can convince ourselves that
it's indeed not that much more expensive
in a normal processor we would have a
program counter that we use to access
the instruction cache to fetch our
instructions because this is a
superscalar processor we are fetching
more than just one instruction with this
program counter then we get into a
decoder that is capable of decoding
multiple instructions per cycle then a
renamer that gets to read and update the
rat for this thread and once the
instruction is renamed it gets to the
reservation stations and then from here
we send the instructions for execution
and in a Rob we need to track what's the
next committed instruction from this
thread so if we want to add the ability
to simultaneously multi thread another
thread here we definitely need a
separate PC here and we need a logic
that will fetch from these two pieces we
could do this every cycle we fetch from
both of the pieces half of the
instructions or we can actually do one
cycle fetch everything you can from this
PC one cycle fetch everything you came
from this PC so SMT usually refers to
what's happening here but here we could
actually be doing fine grained
multi-threading as far as fetching is
concerned most processors do SMT
actually do it that way decoding is
completely oblivious to where the
instructions came from so we don't
really need to change anything about
their decoding logic the renamer does
the same thing regardless of where the
instruction came from except that the
rat is accesses needs to be different so
now we have two rats one for each thread
that we need to access depending on what
are we renaming after renaming
instructions got separate physical
registers for each thread
so the reservation stations are simply
shared by the two threads the execution
units get to execute the operations with
the values they are given so they have
no clue where the instruction really
came from and then when we get to the RO
B we need to either have a separate
therapy when its own commit point in
which case each of the threads gets to
commit its instruction in order what we
actually put all of the instruction in
some interleaved order in the arrow B in
which case we will not be able to commit
an instruction from one thread until is
all the instructions from it and the
other thread that preceded have been
committed because the rob is a large and
complex piece of hardware typically we
don't do this and we actually suffer
here by just committing the threads
together but if we have sent the
instructions in order to the reservation
stations and there are ro B then the
order in the Rob is still the correct
order it's just at some times we could
have committed a instruction from one
thread but we have to wait for the other
thread to also commit some instructions
before that so it's slightly less
optimal but still works fine the thing
that happens at commit though is that we
deposit the results into the
architectural register file and also
when we send instructions for execution
we send it along with the data that
comes from the IRF our threads do have
different registers R 0 here is not the
same as R 0 here so we need a separate
IRF and a separate path to each of the
RS here and also the separate read ports
here so as you can see the complexity
largely lies in having multiple pieces
and being able to fetch from either of
them and in the logic that immediately
precedes the reservation stations but
the really complicated part of the
processor which is the reservation
stations the broadcast of results and so
on stays the same so this is why the
cost is not twice the cost of the
processor most of the cost of the
processor is in the cache array here the
complex Hardware here the large Rob
where you can insert things and wait for
them to finish and so on
and commit and also the data cache and
what we are really adding is another PC
here same size caches before another rat
another IRF but keep the complex part
alone so that's why the cost is not very
very high